Sutton, S. B. (Silvia Barry), 1940-1997. Papers of Stephanne (Silvia Barry) Sutton, 1965-1968 (inclusive): A Finding Aid.
Sutton, S. B. (Silvia Barry), 1940-1997. Papers of Stephanne (Silvia Barry) Sutton, 1965-1968 (inclusive).
Archives of the Arnold Arboretum of Harvard University, Jamaica Plain, MA 02130.
II A-5.
4 Boxes.
The Stephanne (Silvia) Barry Sutton papers reflect the years from 1965-1968 and primarily focus on the working notes and papers for Sutton's biography of Charles S. Sargent. The collection is maintained in the order created by Stephanne Sutton and obtained during her tenure.
Access to Finding Aid record in Hollis Classic or Hollis.
Current version of this finding aid is available at the Archives of the Arnold Arboretum of Harvard University.
Additional Stephanne (Silvia Barry) Sutton correspondence can be found by searching the Arnold Arboretum Correspondence Index.
With the exception of two files on her work on Joseph Rock (1972-1994) which were acquired by the Arboretum's archives from her long-time friend and literary executor, Phyllis Anderson in January 2000, the Sutton papers reflect the years from 1965-1968, her tenure at the Arboretum, and are maintained in the order she created. (Confidential file: For biographical reference, inserted in the collection is Sutton's personnel folder from the administration files of Arboretum director Dr. Richard A. Howard 1954-1978.). This collection was transferred from the Arnold Arboretum’s departmental holdings to the Arboretum’s Archives in 1984.
Terms of Access
Researchers seeking to examine archival materials are strongly encouraged to make an appointment. The Director, or an office of origin, may place restrictions on the use of some or all of its records. The extent and length of the restriction will be determined by the Director, office of origin, and the Archivist and will be enforced equally for all researchers.
Stephanne (Silvia) Barry Sutton was the author of a biography of the Arnold Arboretum's first director,Charles Sprague Sargent, and of the noted plant explorer, Joseph Rock, who had a long affiliation with the Arboretum. A writer of fiction as well as biography and history, Ms. Sutton was on the staff of the Arboretum from 1963 to 1974.
Born in Ohio in 1940, Sutton graduated from Wells College. After a brief stint at the United Nations in New York, she joined the Arboretum staff as an assistant to the director, Richard Howard. At Howard's request she wrote Charles Sprague Sargent and the Arnold Arboretum (Harvard University Press, 1970) in honor of the centennial of the Arboretum. She also wrote The Arnold Arboretum: the First Century, with a forward by Walter Muir Whitehill (Arnold Arboretum, 1971). As an Honorary Research Fellow of the Arboretum she researched the life and work of Joseph Rock which culminated in her book, In China's Border Provinces: the Turbulent Career of Joseph Rock, Botanist-Explorer (Hastings House, 1974).
Stephanne Sutton went on to write a history of Cambridge: Cambridge Reconsidered: 3 ½ Centuries on the Charles (M.I.T. Press, 1976). She wrote two institutional histories: The Massachusetts General Hospital, 1955-1980 (Little, Brown, 1983) and Crossroads in Psychiatry: A History of the McLean Hospital (American Psychiatric Association, 1986).
Her first novel, The Day the Televisions Stopped was published by Knopf in 1992. She died of cancer in 1997.
During her eleven year career at the Arnold Arboretum, Stephanne Sutton held several titles, including Business Secretary from 1963-1964, Research Fellow from 1965-1967, Archivist in 1967-1969, and Honorary Research Fellow from 1970-1974. While Arboretum director Richard A. Howard was preparing for the upcoming centennial, he and Ms. Sutton decided to produce a biography of Charles S. Sargent. At that time, Sutton was appointed research fellow to write the book.
This collection consists of four archival boxes that span the years from 1965-1968, which primarily reflect Sutton's research for Sargent's biography. Included in the correspondence, 1965-1968, are letters on topics such as Sargent and Olmsted's "Boston Scheme," metropolitan parks, Wilson's expeditions, Sargent biographical material, and Arboretum institutional history. Sutton did extensive research in gathering material from primary sources, such as her letters to Katherine Bunker, who was secretary to Sargent and Wilson. In 1966 Ms. Sutton traveled to England to consult letters from Charles Sargent in the files of Royal Botanical Gardens at Kew, the British Museum of Natural History, and at the Library of the Royal Horticultural Society. Her research resulted in many photocopies of Sargent's letters from institutions and individuals that have strengthened the historical correspondence collection of the Arnold Arboretum.
In addition to correspondence, the files include detailed notes on city parks, pre 1912 letters, Boston and the Arnold Arboretum, Kew Gardens of London, history of science, and the hurricane of 1938. There are a few letters that address institutional business that she answered as the Arboretum archivist. One box in the collection is devoted to drafts of the Sargent book from chapter 1-12.
The collection is maintained in the order created by Stephanne Sutton.
- Box 1
  - Saturday Club, Charles S. Sargent (CSS), Frederick Law Olmsted (FLO), Leech on McKinley (File 1 -)
  - Domestic 1969-1970: S. B. Sutton correspondence (File 2 -)
  - Domestic 1965: S. B. Sutton correspondence (File 3 -)
  - Arboretum History: Richard A. Howard correspondence of C. S. Sargent letters search (File 4 -)
  - New Yorker, Dec. 10, 1966, pp. 149-70 Notes on Sargent's Silva of North America (File 5 -)
  - Articles on Arnold Arboretum (File 6 -)
  - Books: Gen. notes of secondary sources (Veitch, Pinchot, C. S. Sargent) (File 7 -)
  - Sargent Index: manuscript (File 8 -)
  - Manuscript, plant lists, centennial ideas (File 9 -)
  - Answers to queries (File 10 -)
  - Domestic 1967: S. B. Sutton correspondence (File 11 -)
  - Permissions and Related Info (to quote letters) (File 12 -)
  - City Parks 1967 (File 13 -)
  - Notes on letters pre 1912 (File 14 -)
  - Correspondence: January 1966-February 1966 (File 15 -)
  - Domestic Correspondence: March 1966 - December 1966 (File 16 -)
- Box 2
  - Sutton, Stephanne B. Reviews (File 1 -)
  - General Biographical Notes:, including Hunnewell, H. W. Sargent, Misc. -Ewan, John Singer Sargent (File 2 -)
  - Arnold Arboretum Sargent (File 3 -)
  - From C. S. Sargent, misc. unbound, DuPont, Eastwood, Lemmon, Morris Arboretum (File 4 -)
  - Small Guidebook (File 5 -)
  - Muir, John (File 6 -)
  - Arnold Arboretum and City of Boston; including letters from C. S. Sargent: Letters to Pringle, 1876-1879 (File 7 -)
  - Notes on letters in Gray file (File 8 -)
  - S. Sutton - New Book Project (File 9 -)
  - Articles for Publication: Book Review (File 10 -)
  - UK Correspondence - Foreign (File 11 -)
  - KEW Material (File 12 -)
  - Arnold Arboretum - Staff Memos (File 13 -)
  - Smithsonian: Letters to and from C. S.Sargent (CSS), Rose, [Vagey] 1893 (File 14 -)
  - Progress Reports to Richard A. Howard (File 15 -)
  - Mail and Misc. Notes Pending (File 16 -)
  - Photographs (File 17 -)
  - Periodical Literature (File 18 -)
    Notes from Bot. Gaz., Gard. Chron., Transcript
  - Biographic Chart (File 19 -)
  - Misc. Manuscript/Probably by Trelease on Bot. Gardens, with references to Arnold Arboretum (File 20 -)
  - Memo for Dr. E. D. Merrill (File 21 -)
  - Material for Typing (File 22 -)
  - Domestic 1968 (File 23 -)
  - Misc. Notes: esp. C. S. Sargent Family (File 24 -)
  - Misc. Notes: For Sargent Biography (File 25 -)
  - C. S. Sargent, Personal (File 26 -)
  - Post - Mortem (File 27 -)
  - Personal Interviews (File 28 -)
  - Post 1912 - To C. S. Sargent (File 29 -)
  - Miscellaneous Notes (File 30 -)
  - Dr. Woods Taxonomy Class (File 31 -)
  - Post 1960 - Arnold Arboretum (AA) (File 32 -)
  - History of Science (File 33 -)
  - Misc., draft 1 Chapter I (File 34 -)
  - Misc., draft 1 Chapter II (File 35 -)
  - Misc., draft 1 Chapter III (File 36 -)
  - Misc., draft 1 Chapter IV (File 37 -)
  - Misc., draft 1 Chapter V (File 38 -)
  - Misc., draft 1 Chapter VI (File 39 -)
  - Misc., draft 1 Chapter VII (File 40 -)
  - Misc., draft 1 Chapter VIII (File 41 -)
  - Misc., draft 1 Chapter VIII, different version (File 42 -)
  - Misc., draft 1 Chapter IX (File 43 -)
- Box 3
  - Misc., Draft 1, Chapter X (File 1 -)
  - Misc., draft 1 Chapter XI (File 2 -)
  - Misc., draft 1 Chapter XII (File 3 -)
  - Misc., draft 1 Chapter XIII (File 4 -)
  - Misc., draft 1 Chapter XIV (File 5 -)
  - Part II, Chapter X, Wilson at Arnold Arboretum (AA) (File 6 -)
  - Chapter VI Introduction (File 7 -)
  - Chapter VII - X Silva Intro (File 8 -)
  - Chapter I Birth and Family (File 9 -)
  - Chapter II Harvard 1872 (File 10 -)
  - Chapter III Arboretum beginnings (File 11 -)
  - Chapter IV Census background (File 12 -)
  - Chapter V Jesup Collection (File 13 -)
  - Part II - Chapter VIII Intro. to Orient (File 14 -)
  - Part III - Chapter XII Arboretum (File 15 -)
  - Part II - Chapter IX Intro. (File 16 -)
  - Part III - Chapter XI Crataegus, Intro. (File 17 -)
  - Sargent (File 18 -)
  - Part III - Chapter XII, Arnold Arboretum ca. 1900 planting arrangements (File 19 -)
  - NOTE:
    A portion of S. B. Sutton's notes and correspondence relating to the Jesup Wood Collection is filed in Arnold Arboretum archives under VI JC "Jesup Wood Collection." this material was the basis for several pages of Sutton's book on Sargent - chapter titled "In Nation's Forest."
- Box 4
  - Notes made by S. B. Sutton (File 1 -)
  - Davenport, Mrs. Natalie Potter (File 2 -)
  - Batchelder, Katherine Abbott (File 3 -)
  - Correspondence regarding donations (File 4 -)
  - Correspondence: Sargent (File 5 -)
  - Correspondence: Moodly, Ambert G. To Sargent (File 6 -)
  - Correspondence: Nuts (File 7 -)
  - Envelope sent by Steve Spongberg from Japan 1977 (File 8 -)
  - The Endemic Flora of Tasmania - An Exhibition of Watercolors (File 9 -)
  - Merrill Administration (File 10 -)
  - Notes on Plants in Collections (File 11 -)
  - Correspondence: Merrill (File 12 -)
  - Malus sargentii (File 13 -)
  - Correspondence: Wagenknecht - Buxus (File 14 -)
  - Correspondence: Wagenknecht - Christmas plants (File 15 -)
  - Karl Sax (File 16 -)
  - Misc. Correspondence (File 17 -)
  - Publishers Rock (1972-1973): Acquired Jan, 2000 (File 18)
  - J. F. Rock, 1991: Acquired Jan, 2000 (File 19)
  - Harald Beckman paper: "Nazi Studies in China:" Acquired Jan, 2000 (File 20)
  - Publicity Photographs (1972): Acquired Jan, 2000 (File 21)
  - Bernard Harkness pamphlet: Excerpts, Letters of Charles Sprague Sargent to Rochester Park Personnel, Inscribed to Silvia Barry Sutton (File 22)
  - S. B. Sutton book: Cambridge Reconsidered (File 23)
The following are common variations on J. F. Rock and Stephanne Sutton's names:
Barry, Silvia
Rock, J. F. C.
Rock, Joseph Francis Charles
Rock, Joseph
Sutton, Silvia B.
Sutton, Stephanne (Silvia Barry)